

Ciampino (Rome), 00043, Italy

🛮 (+39) 375-5532-369 | 🗷 s.raponi.93@gmail.com | 🌴 https://simoneraponi.github.io/ | 🖸 SimoneRaponi | 🛅 simone-raponi | 🗁 simone-raponi

# **Summary**\_

Dedicated AI/ML Cybersecurity Engineer at Equixly with a Ph.D. in Computer Science, specializing in Cybersecurity and Artificial Intelligence. Boasting over 5 years in R&D, I've contributed to over 20 scientific articles, authored a book, and hold multiple patents. Passionate about innovation and lifelong learning in the tech frontier.

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_

**Equixly** Remote, Florence

SENIOR AI/ML CYBERSECURITY ENGINEER

- Responsible for the Artificial Intelligence division in Equixly.
- Design and deployment of multiple AI microservices to optimize continuous security testing for APIs.

**Undisclosed** Rome, Italy

SENIOR MACHINE LEARNING ENGINEER

Mar. 2023 - Jun. 2023

• Design and deployment of Al-based Cybersecurity-related solutions for a defense sector enterprise, collaborating closely with institutions and government entities.

#### NATO-STO Center for Maritime Research and Experimentation (CMRE)

La Spezia, Italy

MACHINE LEARNING SCIENTIST

Jul. 2021 - Mar. 2023

- Main contributor of the PROMENADE European project.
- · Development of Encoder-Decoder Seq2Seq models with LSTMs to forecast vessel trajectories using AIS data.

#### **Iberdrola Innovation Middle East**

Doha, Qatar

MACHINE LEARNING SCIENTIST INTERN IN THE SMART GRID LAB

(Jun. - Aug. 2019) (Mar - Apr. 2021)

- Design and deployment of LSTM-based noise prediction models to optimize noise management in Power Line Communication (PLC) systems.
- · Development distributed algorithms for data acquisition across geographically dispersed PLC devices, enhancing system reliability.

Telefonica Research Barcelona, Spain

MACHINE LEARNING AND BIG DATA SCIENTIST INTERN

Jul. 2018 - Aug. 2018)

Analysis and Experimentation of Al's impact on the privacy of users while interacting with Internet services.

#### **Hamad Bin Khalifa University**

Doha, Qatar

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Jan. 2018 - Apr. 2021)

- TA for a suite of specialized courses: Security Risk Analysis, Multimedia Security, Distributed Systems Security, Computer Engineering Winter Program, and Open Source Intelligence in Cyberspace.
- · Delivery of interactive lectures, design and evaluation of examinations, projects, and lab assignments to advance practical and theoretical understanding in cybersecurity.

# **Education**

# **Hamad Bin Khalifa University**

Doha, Qatar

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Jan. 2018 - Apr. 2021

Jan. 2016 - Oct. 2017

- Awards: Best Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering.
- Thesis: Al-driven Detection of Cybersecurity-related Patterns.
- Outcomes: 1 book, 11 Int. conference papers, 10 Int. journal papers, 2 patents, 1 encyclopedia entry.
- Granted funds of \$120.000.

### Sapienza University of Rome MASTER'S DEGREE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

Rome, Italy

- Thesis: Geographical De-anonymization of Crowds in the Dark Web.
- Final Mark: 110/110 summa cum laude.
- Publication of thesis dissertation to IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems.
- Publication of thesis dissertation extension to IEEE Transactions on Services Computing.

### Sapienza University of Rome

Rome, Italy

Sep. 2012 - Jan. 2016

BACHELOR'S DEGREE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Thesis: An Administrative Model for Attribute-Based Access Control.
- · Final Mark: 110/110 summa cum laude.

# **Publications**

### **PATENTS**

**US Patent App. 16/657,088**, Methods and Systems for Verifying the Authenticity of a Remote Service **US Patent App. 16/880,525**, Online Account Access Recovery System and Method Utilizing Secret Splitting

#### Воокѕ

2021 New Dimensions of Information Warfare, R. Di Pietro, S. Raponi, M. Caprolu, S. Cresci, Springer Nature

#### JOURNAL PAPERS

- Monitoring of Critical Undersea Infrastructures: the Nord Stream and Other Recent Case Studies, G. Soldi, D. Gaglione, S.
- 2023 Raponi, N. Forti, E. D'Afflisio, P. Kowalski, L. M. Millefiori, D. Zizzis, P. Braca, P. Willet, A. Maguer, S. Carniel, G. Sembenini, C. Warner, IEEE Aerospace and Electronic Systems Magazine.
- PAST-AI: Physical-layer Authentication of Satellite Transmitters via Deep Learning, G. Oligeri, S. Sciancalepore, S. Raponi, R. Di Pietro, IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security (TIFS).
- Fake News Propagation: A Review of Models, Datasets, and Insights, S. Raponi, Z. Khalifa, G. Oligeri, R. Di Pietro, ACM Transactions on the Web.
- Sound of Guns: Digital Forensics of Gun Audio Samples meets Artificial Intelligence, S. Raponi, I. Ali, G. Oligeri, Springer Nature Multimedia Tools and Applications.
- 2021 Long-Term Noise Characterization of Narrowband Power Line Communications, S. Raponi, J. Fernandez, A. Omri, G. Oligeri, IEEE Transactions on Power Delivery.
- 2021 Cryptomining Makes Noise: Detecting Cryptojacking via Machine Learning, M. Caprolu, S. Raponi, G. Oligeri, R. Di Pietro, Computer Communications (COMCOM).
- A Longitudinal Study on Web-Sites Password Management (in)Security: Evidence and Remedies, M. Caprolu, R. Di Pietro, S. Raponi, S. Sciancalepore, P. Tedeschi, IEEE Access.
- Vessels Cybersecurity: Issues, Challenges, and the Road Ahead, M. Caprolu, R. Di Pietro, S. Raponi, S. Sciancalepore, P. Tedeschi, IEEE Communication Magazine.
- Nationality and Geolocation-Based Profiling in the Dark (Web), M. La Morgia, A. Mei, E. Nemmi, S. Raponi, J. Stefa, IEEE Transactions on Services Computing (TSC).
- FORTRESS: An Efficient and Distributed Firewall for Stateful Data Plane SDN, M. Caprolu, S. Raponi, R. Di Pietro, Security and Communication Networks.
- Docker ecosystem Vulnerability Analysis, A. Martin, S. Raponi, T. Combe, R. Di Pietro, Computer Communications (COMCOM).

# CONFERENCE PAPERS

- FRACTAL: single-channel multi-FactoR transaction Authentication through a Compromised TerminAL, S. Sciancalepore, S. Raponi, D. Caldarola, R. Di Pietro, International Conference on Information and Communications Security (ICICS).
- Road Traffic Poisoning of Navigation Apps: Threats and Countermeasures, *S. Raponi, S. Sciancalepore, G. Oligeri, R. Di Pietro*, IEEE Security & Privacy.
- Beyond SolarWinds: The Systemic Risks of Critical Infrastructures, State of Play, and Future Directions, S. Raponi, M. Caprolu, R. Di Pietro, Italian Conference on Cybersecurity (ITASEC).
- New Dimensions of Information Warfare: The Economic Pillar–Fintech and Cryptocurrencies, M. Caprolu, S. Cresci, S. Raponi, R. Di Pietro, International Conference on Risks and Security of Internet and Systems (CRISIS 2021).
- KaFHCa: Key-establishment via Frequency Hopping Collisions, M. Usman, S. Raponi, M. Qaraqe, G. Oligeri, IEEE Conference on Communications (ICC): Communication and Information Systems Security Symposium.
- Next Generation Information Warfare: Rationales, Scenarios, Threats, and Open Issues, S. Raponi, M. Caprolu, R. Di Pietro,
  International Conference on Information Systems Security and Privacy (ICISSP).
- BrokenStrokes: On the (in)Security of Wireless Keyboards, G. Oligeri, S. Sciancalepore, S. Raponi, R. Di Pietro, ACM Conference on Security and Privacy in Wireless and Mobile Networks (WISEC).
- 2019 Intrusion Detection at the Network Edge: Solutions, Limitations, and Future Directions, S. Raponi, M. Caprolu, R. Di Pietro, International Conference on Edge Computing.
- Edge Computing Perspectives: Architectures, Technologies, and Open Security Issues, M. Caprolu, R. Di Pietro, F. Lombardi, S. Raponi, IEEE International Conference on Edge Computing.
- Time-Zone Geolocation of Crowds in the Dark Web, M. La Morgia, A. Mei, S. Raponi, J. Stefa, IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS).
- A Spark is Enough in a Straw World: a Study of Websites Password Management in the Wild, S. Raponi, R. Di Pietro, 14th International Workshop on Security and Trust Management (ESORICS STM).

# **Extracurricular Activity**

#### The Illustrated Machine Learning Website

CO-FOUNDER AND TECHNICAL CONTRIBUTOR

Remote Jan. 2023 -

- https://illustrated-machine-learning.github.io/
- · Creation of visual tools to demystify the elegance and intricate workings of machine learning concepts.

RedHotCyber Remote

TECHNICAL WRITER - ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE TEAM

· Author of insightful content exploring the synergies between Cybersecurity, Artificial Intelligence, and their practical applications.

Apr. 2023 -

· Technical Reviewer of the book: 10 Machine Learning Blueprints you should know for Cybersecurity.

# **Funded Grants**

TECHNICAL REVIEWER

2(	2020	<b>Principal Investigator</b> , Project "Securing Online Transactions" funded within the Technology and	\$90.627.90
۷(		Development Fund (TDF) - Cycle TDF-02, by the Qatar National Research Fund	
20	2019	<b>Principal Investigator</b> , Project "Detecting Cryptojacking in Corporate Network" funded within the	\$13.700
۷(		Innovation Center's Idea Development Fund Grant - Cycle 02	
20	2020	<b>Principal Investigator</b> , Project "Strong Server Authentication for Online Transactions" funded within the	\$13.700
۷(		Innovation Center's Idea Development Fund Grant - Cycle 03, by the Hamad Bin Khalifa University	
20	2020	<b>Research Assistant</b> , Project "Extending Blockchain Technology – A Novel Paradigm and Its Applications to	\$600.000
۷(		Cybersecurity and Fintech" funded within NPRP11S-0109-180242, by the Qatar National Research Fund	

# **Academic Activities**

### **Technical Program Committee**

MEMBER OF THE TECHNICAL PROGRAM COMMITTEE

Jan. 2018 -

- International Conference on Database and Expert Systems Applications (DEXA 2024)
- International Conference on Database and Expert Systems Applications (DEXA 2023)
- International Conference on Information Fusion (FUSION 2023)
- International Conference on Ambient Systems, Networks and Technologies (ANT 2022)
- International Conference on Database and Expert Systems Applications (DEXA 2022)
- International Conference on Ambient Systems, Networks and Technologies (ANT 2021)
- International Conference on Database and Expert Systems Applications (DEXA 2021)
- Symposium on Access Control Models and Technologies (SACMAT 2021)
- International Workshop on Cyber Crime (IWCC 2021)
- International Workshop on Cyber Crime (IWCC 2020)
- International Symposium on Foundations & Practice of Security (FPS 2020)
- International Conference on Ambient Systems, Networks and Technologies (ANT 2020)

### Reviewer

OFFICIAL REVIEWER Jan. 2018 -

- IEEE International Conference on Computer Communication (INFOCOM)
- ACM Conference on Security and Privacy in Wireless and Mobile Networks (WISEC)
- Transactions on Emerging Telecommunications Technologies
- Computer Communications (COMCOM)
- · Computer Networks
- · IEEE Internet of Things Journal
- Pervasive and Mobile Computing
- International Journal of Information Security
- · Journal of Computer Security
- IEEE Access
- · IET Information Security
- · Security and Communication Networks
- Journal of Marine Science and Engineering (JMSE)
- · Mathematical Biosciences and Engineering
- MDPI Applied Sciences

**Session Chair** San Diego, USA

CHAIR

• International Conference on Cloud Computing, Session VII: Cloud Resources Optimization

2019

#### **Co-Founder and Executive Assistant**

Doha, Qatar

ORGANIZER, CO-FOUNDER AND EXECUTIVE ASSISTANT

2019

• Qatar International Cyber Security Contest

Mentor Doha, Qatar

MASTER STUDENT'S MENTOR 2019

- Title: Terminator: a Termination Effect on Symmetric Key Encryption by Hybrid Ransomware, Student: Ahmad Nasser A. A. Alkuwari.
- Title: Unikernels for Web Applications and Services: Analysis, Security Assessment, and Offensive Techniques, Student: Faher Bakri.
- Title: Fake News Propagation Blueprint, Student: Zeinab Khalifa.